<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon against murmuring preached in the Cathedral Church of St. Peter Exon on the XXIXth of May, 1680 / Thomas Long.</title>
            <author>Long, Thomas, 1621-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49131</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2982</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R180131</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09542901</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09542901</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43568</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49131)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43568)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1335:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon against murmuring preached in the Cathedral Church of St. Peter Exon on the XXIXth of May, 1680 / Thomas Long.</title>
                  <author>Long, Thomas, 1621-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 27 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Royston,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title: A sermon preached on the XXIXth of May, 1680.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1660-1688 --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:43568:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43568:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON AGAINST Murmuring: PREACHED in the <hi rend="blackletterType">Cathedral Church</hi> Of St. <hi>PETER</hi> EXON, On the
XXIX<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>May,</hi> 1680.</p>
            <p>By <hi>THOMAS LONG,</hi> D.D. One of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendaries of that
Church.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Exod. xvi. 8.</bibl> 
               <p>Your murmurings are not againſt us, but againſt the
Lord.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Royſton,</hi>
Bookſeller to His moſt, Sacred Majeſty, MDCLXXX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:43568:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43568:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Reverend FATHER in GOD THOMAS LORD Biſhop of
EXETER.</head>
            <p>THIS Sermon not reaching the ears of thoſe for whom it was
chiefly intended, I have by your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips direction offered it to their
hands, that it may be as a Glaſs not only to ſhew them their diſtorted
faces but infectious breaths, which may fix ſome ſpots on the glaſs it
ſelf, but ſuch as (I doubt not) will be eaſily wiped off. I have
attempted a very difficult work, The governing of an unruly evil, for as St.
<hi>James</hi> ſayes, <hi>every kind of beaſts and ſerpents have been
tamed by man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chap. 3.7.</note> except the Serpent that
is within him, <hi>the Tongue, which no man can tame.</hi> It was made to be
our Glory, but we generally turn it to our ſhame, eſpecially while
therewith we ſeem to bleſs God, but curſe and ſpeak evil of thoſe who
bear moſt of his Image, his Magiſtrates and Miniſters, <hi>v.</hi> 9. It
is<pb facs="tcp:43568:3"/>
               <hi>full of deadly poyſon,</hi> ſuch as never hurts leſs
than three at once, the perſon ſlandered in his good name, by Calumny; the
perſon that liſteneth to him, in his Charity, by Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice and evil
ſurmiſes; and himſelf moſt of all, by doing the Devils work in
ſlandering his brethren, <hi>v.</hi> 8. It is a <hi>Fire,</hi> ſaith St.
<hi>James, v.</hi> 6. and the worſt of fires, for it is, <hi>ſet on, fire
of hell;</hi> (i.e.) the Devil the father of lyes; He is that god of Contention
who imploys theſe Boutefeaus as <hi>Mars</hi> did his Prieſts to ſcatter
coals of fire in the Temple and inflame the whole courſe of Nature. Other
evils may be ſeen and avoided, but this ſhoots out arrows that fly as
inviſibly in the day as in the dark; it is of ſuch a Verſatile and
<hi>Proteus</hi>-like nature, that no knot can hold it, but it defies the Laws
of God and man. <hi>Our tongues, are our own, we ought to ſpeak, who is Lord
over us?</hi> Pſal. 12.</p>
            <p>I ſhould not have enlarged this diſcourſe but that I
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Calumny is become the <hi>malus genius</hi> of the Nation, which
ſeems to be poſſeſſed not with a dumb but a talka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive ſpirit, that
hath turned Religion into lying and ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering. And ſuch mens
<hi>Religion,</hi> St. <hi>James</hi> aſſures us, <hi>is vain, ch.</hi>
1.26. 'Tis like that wherewith the Votaries of <hi>Mercury</hi> did worſhip
him by caſting ſtones at his Image and murdering their brethren in
<hi>Effigie.</hi>Our Apoſtle diſcovers the root of this evil to be a bitter
zeal, or <hi>envy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſtrife in the heart:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chap.
3.14.</note> the bliſtering of the tongue is cauſed by an ulcerous heart;
and 'tis from within out of<pb facs="tcp:43568:3"/>the heart that all theſe impurities do
proceed. Wherefore according to our Saviours method, I have endeavoured to
cleanſe firſt that which is within, and to ſuppreſs the firſt motions
of murmuring and diſcontent, by applying the lenitives of Right reaſon and
Chriſtian Religion which teacheth us to be of a meek and calm, a cool and
quiet Spirit, to do our own buſineſs, and be content with ſuch things as
we have, and not to quarrel at the providences of God and the Adminiſtration
of publick affairs.</p>
            <p>But now men are grown <hi>preſumptuous, ſelf-willed, they are
not afraid to ſpeak evil of dignities and things which they underſtand
not,</hi> 2 Pet. 2.10. They are not afraid to inſinuate as if the King
favoured the Plot, which hath been declared to be againſt His Majeſties
perſon, and the Eſtabliſhed Religion. They quarrel the Succeſſion,
and would put by the true and undoubted Heir. They inſinuate that His
Majeſty is no friend to Parliaments, and would Rule us by an Arbitrary power.
And as to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> they accuſe it for declining apace
to Popery, and approving Popiſh, Socinian and Pelagian Doctrines, as
<hi>Lewes du Moulin,</hi> and the Author of the <hi>Celeuſma;</hi> when it is
confeſſed by foreign Divines, that it is the greateſt fence againſt
thoſe pernicious errors. They talk as if the Church Governours were mere
Thorns, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of the Devil, exerciſing Tyranny and
Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, whereas the termes of Conformity as to the<pb facs="tcp:43568:4"/>people,
are confeſſed to be much more facile, than ever they were ſince the
firſt Reformation. And in truth the Indulgence granted to ſuch men hath
deſtroyed more by 1000 to one, than that which they call perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution
<hi>(i.e.)</hi> the execution of good laws. They tell the people of an utter
impoſſibility of Conforming to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> becauſe of
many heinous ſins in that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity, (<hi>Baxter</hi>'s Plea for peace,)
and that the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts are generally guilty of Perjury. And theſe baits
are diſperſed through the Nation, and greedily ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by the
Credulous people who conſider not what deadly hooks are under them. And how
great a matter a little of ſuch wild fire kindleth! Againſt theſe falſe
ſuggeſtions and dangerous murmurings, the enſuing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe is
intended.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Perſians</hi> were wont to obſerve an Anniverſary
Feſtival which they called the <hi>death of Vices;</hi> and as an Embleme
thereof, they deſtroyed as many Serpents as they found in the Land. I could
not deviſe how to celebrate this happy Feſtival better than by
endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the mortification of thoſe murmuring and diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented vices
which were the cauſe of our former troubles, and reduced us to ſo low a
condition, that none but Gods own hand could deliver us, as with all
thankfulneſs we acknowledge. But as <hi>Ezra</hi> ſays, ch. 9.13. <hi>If
after all that is come upon us for our evil deeds, for which God hath
puniſhed us leſs than we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve,<pb facs="tcp:43568:4"/>and hath-given us ſuch
deliverance as this, we ſhould again break his Commandments,</hi> and neither
fear him for his Judgments, nor obey him for his Clemency, but continue to be
as our Fathers were, a mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring and rebellious generation, may not our
<hi>God be juſtly angry with us, till he have conſumned us ſo that there
be no remnant nor eſcaping?</hi> May we not fear that he will deal with us as
he did with the murmuring <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> who for forty years together
under the various and miraculous diſpenſations of mercies and judgments
ſo grieved his Holy Spirit that he <hi>Swore in his wrath they ſhould never
enter into his reſt?</hi> Pſal. 95. Our ſins have really brought us to
that brink of deſtruction which our guilty fears make us to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend with
horror, and yet we ſtrive with all our might to caſt each other into that
gulf which like an open Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre is prepared to ſwallow us all.
<hi>Archimedes</hi> is ſaid to have invented ſuch an Engine, as if he could
have found where to ſix it, he would have undertaken by it to remove the
Globe of the Earth out of its place. This Engine ſome Mathematicians
ſuppoſe to have been a Screw; which loſt invention, ſome of our Age
have recovered. And if male-contented ſpirits be permitted to inſinuate to
the hearts of the credulous people, their fears and jealouſies, their lyes
and ſlanders, their murmur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and diſcontent, they would in a ſhort
time remove the well Eſtabliſhed Foundations of Church and State. 
<pb facs="tcp:43568:5"/>The God of Peace, Unity and Concord who ſtilleth the raging of
the Sea, allay the madneſs of ſuch people. 
<q rend="inline">"And give us all that peace which the world cannot
give; that our hearts may be ſet to obey his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, and alſo that
by him we being defended from the fear of our enemies, may paſs our time in
reſt and quietneſs, through the merits of Jeſus Chriſt our
Saviour.</q>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>So daily prayeth Your Lordſhips moſt Humble and
Obliged Servant, THO. LONG.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:43568:5"/>
            <head>A SERMON AGAINST Murmuring. 
<q>
                  <bibl>Eccleſiaſtes vii. 10.</bibl> 
                  <p>Say not thou, what is the cauſe that the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer days were
better than theſe? For thou doſt not inquire wiſely concerning
this.</p>
               </q> 
            </head>
            <p>THERE is nothing wanting to complete the Solemnity of this Day, or
indeed the happineſs of the Whole Nation, beſides Thankful and Obedient
hearts to God and the King, for the many incomparable bleſſings which under
them we now enjoy. That character which the Royal Prophet gives,
<hi>Pſal.</hi> 144. of a <hi>bleſſed people,</hi> agrees well with us:
for firſt, (which is the foundation of all) we have the <hi>Lord to be our
God,</hi> v. laſt. And our God hath <hi>given Salvation to our King,
ver.</hi> 10. He hath <hi>delivered</hi> David <hi>his Servant from the peril
of the Sword.</hi> And again, he hath <hi>delivered<pb n="2" facs="tcp:43568:6"/>him from
the hand of ſtrange children, whoſe mouth ſpeaketh of vanity, and their
right hand is a right hand of falſhood.</hi> And now <hi>our Sons grow up as
young plants,</hi> and <hi>our daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are as the poliſhed corners of the
Temple, our Garners are full, affording all manner of ſtore; our Sheep bring
forth thouſands and ten thouſands in our ſtreets. There is no decay</hi>
(of Trade) <hi>no leading into Captivity.</hi> Only we cannot ſay, <hi>there
is no complaining in our ſtreets.</hi> This ſin lyeth as an indeleble
reproach upon our Nation. We <hi>Engliſh</hi>-men never know when we are
well. But what ſhall we ſay? when the moſt proſperous raign of
Peaceable <hi>Solomon</hi> was diſturbed with the Murmurings of
Male-contents, it is no wonder if it be ſo with us. Every ear is filled with
the hiſſing of ſuch Serpents, and the noiſe which they make among the
Thickets of the people; but it will require the wiſdom of <hi>Solomon</hi> to
charm them; and he did it ſo effectually, that though they did ſome time
hiſs at him, yet they could never hurt him, for there was peace all the days
of <hi>Solomon.</hi> And that it may be ſo with us, I ſhall follow the
method preſcribed in the Text, where, 
<list>
                  <item>Firſt, We have a Royal Prohibition, <hi>Ne dicas, ſay
not thou.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Secondly, We have the ſin deſcribed againſt which the
Prohibition lyeth, which by conſent of the beſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitors is a
murmuring and repining at the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Diſpenſations of God, and the
Adminiſtration of Publick affairs by our Governors.</item>
                  <item>Thirdly, We have the ſecret and ſubtile pretences by
which it inſinuates it ſelf to the hearts of the people, <hi>What is the
cauſe?</hi> and a falſe and odious compariſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the former and the
preſent times, <hi>The former times were better than theſe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:43568:6"/>And Fourthly, The folly and impiety of
ſuch ſecret and miſchievous Arts, <hi>Thou doſt not inquire wiſely
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, Of the Royal Prohibition, <hi>Say not thou,</hi> that is,
Though you queſtion the King's Prerogative, yet quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel not with the
Prerogative of God by whom Kings Reign and Princes decree judgment; as if he
did not ſet fit Governours over us, or did not ſtill retain a power over
them, who hath the hearts of all Kings in his hands, and diſpoſeth of them
to his own wiſe and gracious ends either for the puniſhment or proſperity
of a Nation: If the former days were better, it was God's will to have them
ſo; and the preſent are not ſo bad, but we by our ingratitude deſerve
to have them worſe: If we will not ſubmit to <hi>Solomons</hi> rod, God may
ſend a <hi>Rehoboam</hi> to chaſtiſe us with Scorpions. Know therefore
that this ſin doth not terminate in the perſons or government of our
Princes, but invades the Throne of God; as <hi>Moſes</hi> told the
<hi>Iſraelites, your murmuring is not againſt us, but againſt the
Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ex.</hi> 16.8.</note> And therefore
<hi>Solomon</hi> ſtrikes a blow at the root of this ſin, the <hi>ne
dicas</hi> is <hi>ne dicas corde,</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit not a diſcontented thought: for
as where the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent gets in his head, he eaſily skrews in his whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
ſo where the heart is ſowred with a little of this Leaven, it ferments and
envenometh the whole man, infects the neighbourhood and troubleth the whole
Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Solomon</hi> expounds the <hi>ne dicas</hi> in the Text, by <hi>ne
maledicas, ch.</hi> 10.20. for to murmur is <hi>ſecretò
maledicere;</hi> and we are not to ſpeak evil of the Rulers of the people
<hi>ne in Conſcientiâ,</hi> not under a pretence of Conſcience;
becauſe we muſt ſubmit for Conſcience-ſake; we may not do it <hi>in
ſcientia,</hi> not ſpeak the evil we know by them. It is not fit to ſay
to a King <hi>Thou art wicked.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi>
34.18.</note> Much leſs<pb n="4" facs="tcp:43568:7"/>maiſt thou do it <hi>in
conclavibus</hi> among thy Confidents, in private meetings. It is probably
conjectured that <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> had reſpect to <hi>Jeroboam</hi> and his
confederates, 1 <hi>Kings.</hi> 12.26. <hi>Dixit corde, He ſaid in his heart,
now ſhall the kingdom return to the houſe of David.</hi> He had learnt by
<hi>Shimei</hi>'s puniſhment not to rail or conſpire openly againſt the
King, but contrived ſecretly; for though it be ſaid that he lift up his
hand againſt the King, it was not in open rebellion, for there was no war in
<hi>Solomon</hi>'s days; but the phraſe ſignifyeth, <hi>juramento ſe
obligavit,</hi> he and his confederates entred into a Covenant againſt the
King, the miſchievous effects whereof though they were ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt by the
wiſdom of <hi>Solomon</hi> all his days, yet they brake out in the days of
his Succeſſor, and they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain even of <hi>Solomon</hi> himſelf,
<hi>Thy Father made our yoke grievous,</hi> 1 Kings 12.4. <hi>Now therefore
make thou the grievous ſervice of thy father, and his heavy yoke which he put
upon us, lighter;</hi> And yet we read not of any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution except for the
building of Gods houſe, or the neceſſary ſupport of his own, to both
which the people for the moſt part offered willingly. Nevertheleſs this
gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and peaceable Prince had many enemies who hated him, as
<hi>Davids</hi> enemies did without a cauſe.<note place="margin">1
<hi>Kings.</hi> 2.15.</note> They ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged that God as well as his father
deſigned him for the Crown, and ſetled it on his head againſt all
oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, for <hi>Adonijah</hi> uſurped the kingdom, <hi>Abiathar,
Joab</hi> and <hi>Shimei</hi> abetted the Uſurpation, and were all defeated.
God appearing for <hi>Solomon</hi> not once or twice for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of
him from ſuch enemies, was a daily miracle. But <hi>Jeroboam, Solomons</hi>
ſervant whom he had preferred and greatly honoured, was his moſt dangerous
and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable enemy who filled the peoples hearts with fears and
jealouſies, and their mouths with complaints of his Government; and very
induſtrious he was to find out<pb n="5" facs="tcp:43568:7"/>ſome real cauſe for his
complaints, but finding none, he could only keep the people alarmed with the
ſeditious Queries in the Text, <hi>what is the cauſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This being the Sin forbidden in the Text I ſhall aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate it,
1. From the Cauſes, 2. From the Effects of it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Cauſe</hi> in general is the <hi>luſts of
men.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ex vitio malignita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis humanae vetera
lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantur, praeſentia faſtidio habentur.</hi> Tacitus.</note> So <hi>S.
Jude</hi> deſcribes <hi>Murmurers</hi> to be ſuch as <hi>walk after their
own luſts, ver.</hi> 16. For when men are reſolved to enjoy their luſts,
they will indure no reſtraint from God: or man, be their laws never ſo
eaſie or equal: every one of them hath the mind of an Emperor, to live above
the Laws themſelves, and to make their will a Law to others. And hence it is
that they would heap up Governours to themſelves as they heap up Teachers, or
rather uſurp both thoſe Offices to themſelves, that it might be with them
as when there was no King in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> every one might do what
ſeemeth good in his own eyes. <hi>S. Jude v.</hi> 16. calls them
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, complainers of their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
condition, as too narrow and uneaſie for their great Souls, which they think
fit and able Intelligences to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the higheſt orbs of Magiſtracy and
Miniſtry.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſays it proceeds from ſelf-love,
and a fond conceit of our own parts and merits, for no man thinks too highly of
himſelf but he thinks too meanly of others. <hi>I am not as other men,</hi>
ſays the Phariſee, <hi>nor as this Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lican.</hi> Some reſpect ſuch a
perſon is content to allow the Worthies of former ages, who are removed out
of his his way, and cannot rival him in his deſigns. 
<q> 
                  <l>Sed niſi quae terris ſemota ſuiſque</l> 
                  <l>Temporibus defuncta videt, faſtidit &amp; odit.</l>
               </q> If
virtue it ſelf were incarnate among ſuch, they would look on her with an
evil eye. The <hi>Phariſees</hi> ſeemed much affected with the Sufferings
of the ancient Prophets, when at the ſame time they perſecuted the Son of
God<pb n="6" facs="tcp:43568:8"/>by whom they were all inſpired. So the Poetaſters in
<hi>Virgils</hi> age, publickly read the harſh Poems of <hi>Ennius,</hi>
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſing him whom all ages ſince have deſervedly admired. And on this
account <hi>Jeroboam</hi> and the Malecontents in his days magnified
themſelves as if they were thoſe Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies of the field, to one of which
<hi>Solomon</hi> in all his glory was not to be compared. There is ſcarce a
Potſherd though newly taken from the earth, though empty and crazy, but if it
be not preſently gilded over and made a veſſel of honour, is ready to
expoſtulate with the Potter, why haſt thou made me thus?</p>
            <p n="3">3. This humor proceeds not only from a mans ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed
worth, but from his real weakneſs. It is <hi>impoten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia
ſpiritûs,</hi> the want of power to govern our own ſpirits that makes
us impatient of the government of others. The ſhalloweſt rivers run with
the greateſt noiſe. And in all nature the weakeſt things are moſt
querulous and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>governable. Children will be froward, as well full as
faſting; the weakneſs of their reaſon and judgment makes their deſires
and paſſions ſo extravagant and impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous. The Olive and the Vine can
content themſelves with their own fatneſs, and the good man is ſatisfied
from himſelf. As <hi>Cincinnatus</hi> and the worthies of old <hi>Rome,</hi>
who could command as Generals in the Camp, and adviſe as Oracles in the
Senate; and when their Countrey was ſafe, return again to their little
Cottages and the Plough. It is the ſpiny bramble that is alway aſpiring and
in perpetual motion until it kindle a fire to conſume it ſelf and the
Cedars in <hi>Lebanon, Judges</hi> 9.15.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Another ingredient is guiltineſs, which always makes
men jealous and ſuſpicious, eſpecially of ſuch as are in Authority. And
as guilt cauſeth fear, ſo fear pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth hatred of thoſe whom they have
offended <hi>(i.e.)</hi> the Legiſlators, whom not being able to oppoſe by
force,<pb n="7" facs="tcp:43568:8"/>they ſeek to undermine by fraud and ſecret
practices: As ſome malefactors that are purſued joyn themſelves to the
purſuers, and by falſe ſuggeſtions and ſubtle inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions raiſe
ſuſpicion on others to clear themſelves. The moſt guilty are moſt
clamorous and complain firſt, and feign themſelves moſt diligent
againſt the evils of the times, which they themſelves have cauſed and
continued. What is the Cauſe, ſay they, of the preſent troubles? when
they and their fathers houſe are thoſe that trouble our <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el.</hi>
Which brings us to a ſecond Aggravation of this Sin:</p>
            <p n="2">2. The miſchievous <hi>Effects</hi> of it; for 1. as
<hi>S. Paul</hi> tells us, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1. when men <hi>are lovers of
themſelves, cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, boaſters, proud, diſobedient to parents,
unthankful,</hi> &amp;c. then <hi>perillous times ſhall come.</hi> Nothing
doth more por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the diſpleaſure of God againſt a Nation, than when he
permits popular clamours and tumults to invade the publick authority, and the
contumacy of thoſe that break the laws, to outbrave the courage of thoſe
that ſhould execute them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>St. Paul</hi> tells us of another effect,
<hi>Phil.</hi> 2.14. where he joyns murmurings and diſputings. Such men are
ever more ready to cenſure and controll than to obey the laws of their
Superiours. They are ſtarting of ſcruples and queries not ſo much to
ſatisfie themſelves, being reſolved never to be ſatisfied, as to
diſtract others: And as <hi>Pliny</hi> obſerves of the Scorpion, that he
doth <hi>(meditari vulne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra)</hi> dart forth his ſting on every motion of his
body, leſt any occaſion of doing miſchief ſhould be omitted; <hi>Et
ſi non aliqua nocuiſſet mortuus eſſet:</hi> In all companies, upon
every occaſion ſome men ſhew their diſcontent by ſowre looks and
ſullen behaviours, their envyous grudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and vindictive groans. Their
Faſting when they ſhould feaſt, and rejoycing when they ſhould mourn,
Condemning the Laws which they ſhould obey, do ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt<pb n="8" facs="tcp:43568:9"/>that the ſpirit by which they live and breath is a ſpirit of
Contradiction. 
<q rend="inline">"The rude people <hi>(ſays the Royal Martyr in
his ch. of Tumults)</hi> are taught firſt to Petition, then to Proteſt,
then to Dictate, then to Command.</q> This was the method uſed in 43, as it
is left on record in the Preface to the Covenant.—
<q rend="inline">"After other means of Supplications,
Remonſtrances, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now at laſt we enter into
a Solemn League and Covenant.</q> And by this method the late Tumults in
<hi>Scotland</hi> commenced into a Rebellion. They ſow the Seeds of Sedition
in private meetings, thence iſſue Petitions, Remonſtrances, and at laſt
the Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticlers appear in armed companies and declare for the Covenant
againſt the Oath of Supremacy, and the Kings uſurped power in
Eccleſiaſtical affairs, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn the obſervation of the 29th of
<hi>May</hi> as Superſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. And too many in <hi>England</hi> were on
Tiptoe to have danced after this Scotch Pipe. And ſo we come,</p>
            <p n="3">3. To the <hi>laſt</hi> effect of theſe murmurings,
which <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> hath obſerved, <hi>numb.</hi> 17.10. where he
expreſly calls them <hi>Rebels.</hi> And we all know that murmurings were
thoſe winds which blew up and ſcattered thoſe coals of jealouſie which
kept the whole Nation in a flame twenty years together, and now threaten a new
Conflagration. For as the Learned <hi>Verulam</hi> obſerves, there is only
this difference between ſeditious murmurings and ſeditious tumults, that
the one is the Brother and the other the Siſter; Tumults and Seditions are
more maſculine, but Murmurings as malicious. Which the Ancients have
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geniouſly deſcribed in the Fable of the Giants which the earth brought
forth, who for warring againſt the gods were ſmitten with Thunderbolts, and
to revenge their death, the Earth laboured again, and brought forth Fame. The
Moral is this: The Common people are that<pb n="9" facs="tcp:43568:9"/>Earth who oppoſing
their Governours were ſubdued by force of Arms; but to be avenged of them
they brought forth Fame, <hi>(i.e.)</hi> Seditious reports and ſlanders,
which had ſuch ſecret motions and ſubtle evaſions that the gods
themſelves <hi>(i.e.)</hi> their Governors could not ſilence them. Which is
the third thing propoſed, the ſubtle pretences by which this luſt
inſinuates it ſelf, <hi>what is the cauſe,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>As if they had ſaid: The preſent times are much dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated
from the former, and are ſtill growing worſe. Atheiſin is increaſed and
Godlineſs diſcouraged, vile per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are exalted and ſuch as are truly
honourable deſpiſed, and there are few or none that are valiant for the
truth, or ſhew their zeal for the Lord of Hoſts. In former times men were
more active for Reformation of abuſes both in Church and State, there wanted
not ſome that would tell King <hi>David</hi> his faults to his face, and
accuſe him for a man of bloud; and if he ſeemed not to hear the Curſes of
<hi>Shimei,</hi> there was a <hi>Sheba</hi> to blow a Trumpet and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim,
<hi>Every man to his tents, O Iſrael.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Kings</hi>
12.16.</note> Nay there was an <hi>Achitophel</hi> whoſe Counſel was
eſteemed as an Oracle of God, that prevailed with <hi>Abſalom</hi> to
undertake to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs the Grievances of the people,<note place="margin">2
<hi>Sam.</hi> 16.15.</note> and theſe made their party ſtrong enough to
drive the King out of all his ſtrong holds, and chaſe him not only from one
mountain to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but from one Kingdom to another, and at laſt to
<hi>bind the King himſelfe in chains, and his Nobles in fetters of Iron.</hi>
And this honour had thoſe ancient Saints.</p>
            <p>And as for Church Reformation we have the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of thoſe
Godly zealots that publickly proteſted againſt thoſe Superſtitious
vanities and heatheniſh cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms which <hi>David</hi> would have joyned to
the Worſhip of God, ſuch as his bowing and dancing before the Ark, his
appointing ſeveral Orders of Prieſts and Levites with<pb n="10" facs="tcp:43568:10"/>Vocal and Inſtrumenral muſick for the Service of the Temple, who
were to praiſe God with the Pſaltery and Harp, and <hi>to ſtand every
morning and evening to praiſe God, for his mercy endureth for every,</hi> 1
<hi>Chron.</hi> 23.30. 
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Kings</hi> 12.28.</note> And as for the
coſtly ornaments, the veſſels of Gold and Silver, the Painted and Carved
works, there were thoſe that brake them down with Axes and Hammers, and took
to themſelves the Houſes of God in poſſeſſion, yea they propagated
a more ſimple and purer Worſhip, ſuch as that of <hi>Jeroboam</hi> who
brought their houſhold-gods to their doors, and ſet up Calves at
<hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi> making Prieſts of the meaneſt of the
people, who were conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the free-will Offerings of their Brethren.</p>
            <p>But now though this liberty of Conſcience be denyed us, and King
<hi>Solomon</hi> hath eſtabliſhed by a Law all that <hi>David</hi>
intended; though he have built and beautified the Temple, and obligeth us to
that publick place of Worſhip, and enjoyns us to Worſhip and fall down and
kneel as if God were there preſent:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi>
95.6.</note> Though he requires an Uniformity to all thoſe Forms of Prayer
and Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving which were compoſed by <hi>David</hi> and
<hi>Aſaph,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.30. and to joyn with <hi>the Levites
which were the Singers, being arayed in white linnen, having Cymbals,
Pſalteries and Harps, to make one ſound in Praiſing and Thanking the
Lord,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 5.12. Yea though <hi>Solomon</hi> do ſtint the
Spirit of prayer in Gods Miniſters, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids them to be <hi>raſh with
their mouths,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5.2.</note> and <hi>to
let their tongues be haſty to utter any thing before the Lord,</hi> as if our
extemporary prayers were the Sacrifices of fools: yet may we not complain or
ſo much as Petition againſt theſe grievous impoſitions. Nay what is yet
worſe, we are required to renounce the Vow at <hi>Hebron,</hi> and the Solemn
League which <hi>Jeroboam</hi> and his godly party took with hands lifted up to
heaven, and inſtead of the Vow<pb n="11" facs="tcp:43568:10"/>to God, we are told we
muſt keep the Kings command and that <hi>in regard of the oath of God,
ch.</hi> 8.2. And we muſt alſo declare that <hi>againſt the King there is
no riſing up,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 30.3.</note> upon any
pretence whatſoever, nor againſt ſuch as are commiſſioned by him; but
<hi>if the ſpirit of</hi> ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate <hi>Rulers riſe up againſt us,
we may not go out of our places,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi>
10.4.</note> nor ſtir beyond our private callings and capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, but
<hi>fear God and the King, and not meddle with them that are given to
change,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 24.21</note> though it be for a
thorow Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation. And in a word, <hi>Solomon</hi> would put ſuch a gag in
our mouths that we may not ſo much as demand, <hi>What is the cauſe that
the former days were better than theſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I have ſaved theſe men the labour in ſumming up all the
Cauſes of the pretended evils of their-times; and how frivolous they are,
appears evidently by this, that <hi>David</hi> appointed nothing for the
publick Worſhip of God but what he graciouſly accepted. And all that
<hi>Solomon</hi> injoyned was immediately directed by the Spirit of God, and
ſtands recorded in the Holy Scriptures as ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral rules to be obſerved in
the publick Worſhip of God to all ſucceeding ages.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Solomon</hi> well knew that the evils in his days were
cauſed by the Complaints of thoſe malicious men who were enemies to his
Fathers Government as well as his own, that they intended to bring his Perſon
and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment into contempt, and minded not the redreſs of publick
grievances as much as of their private fortunes: and if the times were evil,
they took a direct courſe to make them worſe, by endeavouring to overthrow
all thoſe Conſtitutions which both <hi>Solomon</hi> and his father
<hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> had well eſtabliſhed. He knew that if theſe
Male-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents were permitted to ſow theſe ſeeds of Rebellion, they would
like the Dragons teeth ſowed by <hi>Gadmus</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:43568:11"/>ſpring
up into Armed men that would deſtroy their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</p>
            <p>God forbid that we ſhould be inſenſible of our own ſins,
or of the tokens of Gods wrath that are upon us. That our Religion ſhould be
as <hi>Sion</hi> of old whom no man cared for, or that we ſhould ſuffer our
ſelves to be led into Captivity as we were brought out of it, as men in a
dream. It is our Intereſt as well as our duty to mourn for other mens ſins
as well as our own, but we ſhould do that in ſecret, and take heed that
under a pretence of reproving their ſins we do not pour out reproach on their
perſons and government, and by ſuch art ſo ſpread abroad their
infirmities as to make a cloak for our own iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. We may alſo be
inſtrumental in a reformation, but we ſhould begin it at the right end, our
own wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed hearts and lives, and not at the Heads of our Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors; to
complain that the days are evil, with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign by ſuch complaints to make
them worſe; to ſearch after remote and ſecret cauſes, and overlook
thoſe that are ſo near and obvious in our own boſoms, and with the Harlot
in <hi>Solomon</hi> having overlayed her own child to accuſe a tender
mother,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Kings</hi> 3.20.</note> and ſeek to deprive
her of her living child, is a ſubtle deſign, but ſuch as could not
ſtand the Teſt of <hi>Solomon;</hi> and a greater than <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi>
will judge ſuch men.</p>
            <p>It was obſerved by the Royal Martyr, that whoever intended to
bring forth confuſion in a Church or State, have uſed the Midwifry of
complaints and tumults. By this Artifice <hi>Abſalom</hi> ſtole the hearts
of the people from his Father <hi>David, See thy cauſe is right, but there is
no man deputed of the King to do thee juſtice,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.3.
when the deſign was, <hi>O that I were judge in Iſrael.</hi> And to
facilitate his deſign he remembreth his Vow at <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bron,</hi> that under
pretence of Piety to God he might<pb n="13" facs="tcp:43568:11"/>ſtrengthen his party and
the more impunely caſt off his obedience to his Father. By the like art
<hi>Jeroboam</hi> had ſtoln the hearts of <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Subjects, and
made a great part of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to ſin with him. For though the
founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>Solomons</hi> Government were ſuch as might have made all
<hi>Iſrael</hi> as firm as Mount <hi>Sion</hi> which could not be moved,
though in his days there was a confluence of all thoſe bleſſings whereof
one or two might have made another Nation happy; yet by their whining
murmur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and reſtleſs complaints of heavy yoaks, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching
Idolatry, of the hainous ſins and imminent dangers of the Nation, they did
<hi>(tantum non)</hi> fail but a little of ſubverting the whole frame of the
beſt eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed Government in the world.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Solomon</hi> had a jealous ear which heard all theſe
things, and was aſſiſted with more than humane pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and power to
ſuppreſs them. He cruſheth this Cockatrice in the Egg, and diſcovers
the folly and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety of it. <hi>Thou doſt not inquire wiſely,
&amp;c.</hi> which brings us to the laſt part of the Text, <hi>non ex
ſapientiâ.</hi> Witty men there might be among ſuch <hi>(ingenioſi
in malum publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum)</hi> but they were neither wiſe nor good men in the
ſence of <hi>Solomon.</hi> For whether by wiſdom we underſtand moral
prudence, or (as moſt Expoſitors) true piety and the fear of God, they who
thus cauſleſly murmured againſt the King had neither, they acted both
againſt Reaſon and Religion.</p>
            <p>Firſt againſt <hi>Reaſon.</hi> For what is more irrational
than ſolicitouſly to enquire after the cauſes of thoſe things that are
not? They might as well ask why the Sun had loſt its light, or the
foundations of the earth were removed, which were as true as that the former
days were better than thoſe of <hi>Solomon;</hi> which will appear by a
ſhort view of the Church and State of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> in the days of
<hi>Solomon.</hi> For 1. <hi>In riches and wiſdom</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:43568:12"/>Solomon <hi>exceeded all the Kings of the earth that were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
him,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 10.27. The Veſſels and Utenſils of Gods
Houſe as well as the Kings were of beaten Gold, <hi>for Gold was as common as
ſilver, and ſilver as the ſtones in the ſtreets of Jeruſalem,</hi> 1
<hi>Kings</hi> 9.28. And his Royal Navy commanded the Trade of the world, and
kept his Exchequer always full and running over, bringing home 666 Talents of
Gold at a time, beſides the rich merchandize from <hi>Tyre</hi> and
<hi>Egypt.</hi> There was alſo a general peace to injoy this great plenty,
for <hi>Solomon</hi> was in this a Type of Chriſt, there was neither
adverſary nor evil occurrence, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 4. but all <hi>Judah</hi> and
<hi>Iſrael</hi> which made a prey of each other in the days of
<hi>David,</hi> were united and <hi>dwelt ſafely every man under his own
Vine, and under his own fig-tree from</hi> Dan <hi>to</hi> Beerſheba, there
was a general and perpetual peace all the dayes of <hi>Solomon, ver.</hi> 25.
Which peace was the more admirable becauſe that though <hi>Adonijah</hi> had
uſurped the Kingdom and ſtrengthned himſelf by the heads of divers
factions, <hi>Joab</hi> among the ſouldiers, and <hi>Abiathar</hi> among the
Prieſts, and <hi>Shimei</hi> chief of the <hi>Benjamites;</hi> yet was he
ſetled on his Fathers Throne without ſhedding of bloud or any oppoſition.
His League alſo with <hi>Hiram</hi> deſerves a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark, being a friend to
the True Religion, and the moſt potent and skilful in Sea-affairs. But what
is eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to be noted is, that all theſe bleſſings were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed
to him by a promiſe from God for his father <hi>Davids</hi> ſake.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Kings</hi> 11.12.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. His clemency did adorn his peace, for he pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſuch
offenders as could obtain pardon from themſelves: <hi>Adonijah</hi> that had
uſurped the Kingdom, and <hi>Joab</hi> that had barbarouſly ſlain
<hi>Abner</hi> and <hi>Amaſa</hi> Captains of his Fathers Hoſt, and
<hi>Abiathar</hi> a revolted Prieſt that had ſtrengthned the hands of the
Uſurper, and <hi>Shimei</hi> alſo<pb n="15" facs="tcp:43568:12"/>who having got the
upper ground of <hi>David</hi> ſpit his ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nome in his Royal face, reviling
him <hi>(maledictione forti)</hi> with all the virulence he could, 2
<hi>Sam.</hi> 16.7.</p>
            <p n="3">Yet 3. His clemency was ſeaſoned with juſtice which
was inflicted on incorrigible offenders without reſpect of perſons, high
and low, natives and ſtrangers, parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly on <hi>Shimei</hi> for that
horrid fact on the perſon of his father whom he commanded to be ſlain by
the hand of <hi>Benaiah,</hi> and the kingdom was thereby eſtabliſhed in
the hand of <hi>Solomon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. His Maximes of Government were of infallible and eternal
verity, ſuch as theſe: <hi>Mercy and truth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the King, and by
righteouſneſs ſhall his throne be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 20.28</note> 
               <hi>It is the honour of a King to
ſearch out a matter.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 25.2.</note> 
               <hi>In
the multitude of Counſellors there is peace: But where no counſel is, the
people fall.</hi>
               <note place="margin">11.14.</note> 
               <hi>Righteouſneſs
exalteth a Nation, but ſin is a reproach to any people, Pro.</hi> 14.34.</p>
            <p>And his men were ſuited to his Maxims, men of gravity and
experience, of prudence, piety and mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, ſuch as would have ſecured
the Crown to <hi>Reho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam,</hi> had he not rejected them and inclined to
greener heads that were brought up with him. All theſe bleſſings he
diſpenſed with great wiſdom, having a heart as capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious as the ſand
on the Sea-ſhore. Which wiſdom he acquired partly by giving his heart to
it, but it was perfected by the gift of God. This made his face to ſhine ſo
as he attracted the admiration of all the Kings of the Earth, and the Queen of
the South came from far to be an Ear witneſs of it, and envyed the
happineſs of his Subjects. This wiſdom he demonſtrated to be better than
ſtrength by ſuppreſſing ſtrife and contention in the firſt riſe
of it. He carefully obſerved all the motions of the people, and neglected not
in times of peace to make proviſion for war. He had many fortified Cities,
and<pb n="16" facs="tcp:43568:13"/>40000 ſtalls for the horſes of his Chariots, and
40000 horſe, and his people were as the ſand as for number.
Notwithſtanding all this preparation of Chariots and horſes
<hi>Solomon</hi> knew that Salvation was of the Lord. And that he might obtain
the Lord of hoſts to fight for him, he eſtabliſhed the publick Worſhip
of God through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all his Dominions. This made the Crown on <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi>
head more ſplendid than that wherewith his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther crowned him in the day of
his Eſpouſals. How could he ſtrengthen himſelf more than by making the
building of Gods houſe the foundation of his own? Now whereas the Ark of God
in the days of <hi>David</hi> was in a wandring condition, ſometime drawn
with Oxen and ſometime with Kine, <hi>Solomon</hi> built it a houſe, and
directed the uſe of that houſe to be <hi>a houſe of Prayer,</hi> which
God ſo graciouſly accepted that he promiſed, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 7.14,15.
That <hi>his eyes ſhould be open and his ears attent unto the prayers that
were made in that place.</hi> How irrational was it then for any to complain
that the former days were better than theſe? A King thus ſetled on his
Throne might ſcatter away all evil with his eye, and turn their low
murmurings into loud Acclamations: but what ſhall we ſay? the warm Sun
breeds theſe Vipers and animates them as well as the fire of Contention.
Theſe murmurings abounded not only in the wilderneſs, but in
<hi>Canaan,</hi> a land that flowed with milk and honey, which they turned to
gall and bitterneſs by their diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent; <hi>they deſpiſed that holy
land.</hi> Yea this ſin prevailed againſt our firſt Parents in
Paradiſe, and tempted them by forbidden means to aſpire to greater
happineſs and more knowledge than God thought fit for them, and thereby
turned Paradiſe it ſelf into a Wilderneſs. Yea this reſtleſs luſt
mounted up into heaven, and made ſome of the Angels of God Apoſtates and
Devils. And no<pb n="17" facs="tcp:43568:13"/>wonder then that it poſſeſſeth
thoſe who only by a flaſh of zeal transform themſelves into Angels of
light, and makes them act as incarnate Devils. It was a greater wonder how
<hi>Solomon</hi> could ſhake off theſe Vipers that ſo faſtned on his
hands, and charmed them ſo as they could not hurt him. For no ſooner was
<hi>Solomon</hi> removed but they ſpit their venome in the face of
<hi>Rehoboam</hi> his Son, though <hi>for three years together he walked in the
ways of</hi> David <hi>and</hi> Solomon; but <hi>Jeroboam</hi> in the head of a
Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanted party upbraids the Son with the tyranny of his Father, 1
<hi>Kings</hi> 12.4. <hi>Thy father made our yoke grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous,</hi> and would
impoſe conditions on him, <hi>make thou our yoak lighter and we will ſerve
thee,</hi> otherwiſe they were ready to ſerve him as they ſerved his
father <hi>David;</hi> for becauſe he did not preſently gratifie them, they
ſecond their bold remonſtrance with open defiance, <hi>v.</hi> 16. <hi>What
portion have we in David, &amp;c.</hi> And why in <hi>David?</hi> but to ſhew
that they hated him the more for his ſake for whom God loved him, even his
father <hi>David.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Such complaints are irrational becauſe by them men
create troubles to themſelves and others. Their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcreet fears and
precipitate actions betray them to thoſe dangers they ſeek to avoid, as
children in a boat which they fancy ready to ſink, on one ſide, fly all to
the other and overturn it on themſelves,
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, it is not ſo much the things
we fear or ſuffer as our falſe opinions of them, whereby we torment our
ſelves before our time, yea too many vex and diſquiet themſelves for
thoſe things for which they ſhould rather rejoyce and be thankful. Thus was
<hi>Cain</hi> troubled that his brothers ſacrifice was better accepted. And
<hi>Joſephs</hi> brethren repined at his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment. We call evil good and
good evil; and as chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren cry and grudge, if we be denyed thoſe things
which would prove our ruine.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:43568:14"/>It is our duty therefore to rectifie our
opinions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the true worth and uſefulneſs of things according to
the word of God and right reaſon, and think that beſt which God ſees to
be fitteſt for us; and when he gives us bread, not to turn it into gravel and
ſtones by our diſcontent.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is irrational, becauſe by a cauſleſs reflection
on former, or jealouſie of future times, we deprive our ſelves of preſent
bleſſings, and catching at ſhadows loſe the ſubſtance. Therefore
<hi>Solomon</hi> often commends a chearful enjoyment of the fruit of our
labours, and the portion God hath given us, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9.7. <hi>Eat thy
bread with chearfulneſs, and drink thy wine with a merry heart, for God now
accepteth thy works.</hi> And our Saviour forbids us to be ſolicitous for
what is to come, as <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> doth for what is paſt, <hi>Matth.</hi>
6.34. And the Apoſtle adviſeth us to be <hi>content with ſuch things as
we have,</hi> and ſo doth the Philoſopher,
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commode our ſelves to our
preſent condition, and if our eſtates will not ſtretch to our-minds, to
ſtoop our minds to our eſtates. 
<q>Dona praeſentis cape laetus horae, linque futura.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. It is irrational, becauſe if our condition be bad, this
is a certain mean to make it worſe. It is like the caſting out Devils by
<hi>Peelzebub,</hi> a conjuring up ſuch evil ſpirits as we have not power
to confine or put down again. When men grow weary of the long continued mercies
of God, and loath Manna, it is juſt with God while the meat is yet in our
mouths, to pour his wrath upon our heads, and teach us to know the worth of his
bleſſings by the want of them. God hath exemplarily puniſhed unthankful
murmurers with extraordinary judgements, that all <hi>may hear and fear and do
no more ſo wickedly.</hi> The murmuring Iſraelites that <hi>brought up an 
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:43568:14"/>evil report upon the land, dyed by the plague before the
Lord, Numb.</hi> 14.37. Others of them <hi>periſhed by the deſtroyer,</hi>
1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.10. And thoſe in <hi>Numb.</hi> 11.18. who having Manna
enough to eat, <hi>murmured and wept in the ears of the Lord,</hi> ſaying,
<hi>Who ſhall give us fleſh to eat? for it was well with us in Egypt. The
Lord gave them fleſh to eat till it came forth at their noſtrils, v.</hi>
20. <hi>becauſe they deſpiſed the Lord that was among them, and wept
before him ſaying, Why came we out of Egypt?</hi> And for the puniſhment of
<hi>Corah,</hi> and ſuch as murmured againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and
<hi>Aaron,</hi> the Lord created a new judgment, for the earth opened her mouth
and ſwallowed them up.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.32.</note> And
that people were not purged from that ſin till they were utterly
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, as it was threatned, <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.47,48. <hi>Becauſe thou
ſervedſt not the Lord thy God with joyfulneſs and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of heart
for the abundance of all things: therefore thou ſhalt ſerve thy enemies
which the Lord ſhall ſend againſt thee, in hunger and in thirſt, and in
nakedneſs, and in want of all things, and he ſhall put a yoke of iron on
thy neck until he have deſtroyed thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. It is irrational, becauſe they complain firſt and
moſt who have leaſt reaſon. Many a good man who in <hi>Davids</hi> days
had ſuffered the loſs of all, and came off only with their lives and ſome
marks of their Loyalty in their bodies and eſtates, were abundantly
ſatisfied to ſee the King returned in Peace, and the Ark of God ſetled in
the beauty of holineſs, could ſay with <hi>Mephi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boſheth, Let them take
all for as much as my Lord the King is come to his houſe in peace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.30.</note> and were found faithful and
peaceable in the Land. They were the murmurers who as <hi>Ziba, Sauls</hi>
ſervant, had made themſelves great with the ſpoils of the Crown and
Church lands, but were made to refund a part of it. Though they ſtill enjoyed
not only the publick bleſſings of peace and plenty, and a 
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:43568:15"/>rich trade, and were received not only to mercy but into
favour, and did partake of the Wealthy and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Offices of the Nation,
equally, if not beyond thoſe that had better deſerved them, did yet think
them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves not duly rewarded, (as in truth they were not) and on all
occaſions reproached the footſteps of Gods anointed, and did not only turn
their backs on the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of the King, but lift up their heels againſt
the Ordinances of God alſo.</p>
            <p n="6">6. It is unreaſonable to murmur and repine at thoſe
things in others which they practiſed and allowed in themſelves. They
complained that <hi>Solomon</hi> chaſtiſed them with Rods, when they
wounded him with Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions. They accuſed him for endeavouring to rule by an
Arbitrary power, though he governed himſelf accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the known Laws of
God and the Nation, and often relaxed the ſeverity and ſuſpended the
execution of them, while they lived in a bold contempt and viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them
all. Great cries were raiſed againſt the Oath of God, and the King, and
againſt Uniformity to the Temple Worſhip; when they thought they were all
ingaged by <hi>Jeroboams</hi> Covenant, to bring all within the Kings Dominions
to an Uniformity according to his Directory for Worſhip. A Toleration was
thought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable, when <hi>Jeroboam</hi> had ſet up his Calves, and he
himſelf burnt Incenſe and made Prieſts of the loweſt of the people,
leſt the Kingdom ſhould return to the houſe of <hi>David</hi> (for the
true worſhip of God would reduce them to obedience to their lawful
King.)<note place="margin">1 <hi>Kings</hi> 12.26.</note> 
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Kings</hi> 12.28.</note> But under the
Temple ſervice a Toleration is pleaded for as neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for the eaſe
and liberty of the people, and if it be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed, they complain of Tyranny and
Perſecution, when by this means <hi>Jeroboam</hi> and a few diſſenters
under him deluded the people, and making them believe that he 
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:43568:15"/>and his Calves were the Gods that brought them out of
<hi>Fgypt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>ver.</hi> 28.</note> led them directly
thither, and betrayed them to that abominable Idolatry. So that in truth the
In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence which was granted them did produce more miſchief than all the
puniſhments inflicted by <hi>Solomon,</hi> which they cauſleſly called
perſecution. <hi>Wherefore thou art inexcuſable O man whoever thou art that
judgeſt, for wherein thou judgeſt another thou condemneſt thy ſelf,
ſeeing thou doſt the ſame</hi> (or worſe) <hi>things: And</hi> (though
thou eſcape the judgment of man, yet) <hi>think not that thou ſhalt
eſcape the judgment of God, Rom.</hi> 2.1, <hi>&amp;</hi> 3.</p>
            <p n="7">7. What is more unreaſonable than for men to take
oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to grow more troubleſome from thoſe things which ſhould quiet
them as diſcontented ſpirits are wont to do? Let favour be ſhewed to the
wicked, and he is the more bold and preſumptuous. They turn the grace of God
and the King too into wantonneſs. Every indulgence (as to froward children)
makes them more pettiſh and inſolent, every conceſſion and yielding is
uſed as a ſtep for them to aſcend higher and preſs forward until they
get uppermoſt. The craving humor increaſeth by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fed, and with
<hi>Solomons</hi> horſe-leech thy cry Give, Give, though they have
ſwallowed ſo much that they are ready to burſt. Never was any thing in
the world ſo well eſtabliſhed, but there were ſome envious men that
found fault with it.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, It is irrational, becauſe it is an incurable evil. It
is <hi>opprobrium medicorum,</hi> ſuch a plague of the heart as the beſt
State Phyſicians have not been able to cure. It will not admit a plaiſter
or a medicine to be applied to it. This evil ſpirit though it be not dumb,
yet is it ſo deaf, that it will not hear the voice of any Charmer though he
charm never ſo wiſely. Neither the mercies nor judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, nor the
meekneſs nor miracles of <hi>Moſes</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:43568:16"/>could convince
the murmuring <hi>Iſraelites.</hi> And when ſome of them ſaw
<hi>Corah</hi> and his company ſwallowed up of the earth, yet as if there had
been a tranſmigration of their Souls into their Survivors, the next morning
they murmur again, ſaying, Ye have ſlain the people of the Lord. The
worſt ſort of Spirits that we read of, might be caſt out by Prayer and
Faſting; but this kind can faſt and pray, and ſeemingly reform and
ſweep and garniſh the houſe, and then admit ſeven worſe than it
ſelf, and at the end is worſe than in the beginning. The Scripture compares
this murmuring and rebellious ſpirit to the ſin of Witchcraft which is
ſeldom reclaimed to a pious or ſober temper, for like men in a
Conſumption they ſeem pleaſed with the diſeaſe, and as <hi>Jonah</hi>
they think they do well to be angry with God himſelf, which is the next
particular, it is not only irrational but <hi>irreligious.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe theſe men make lyes their refuge, and ſeek
to hide their ſin under falſe pretences; for it were eaſie to prove, that
no times before <hi>Solomon</hi> were ſo proſperous as his. Though
<hi>David</hi> his Father was a man after Gods own heart, yet neither he nor
the Ark of God could find a reſting place. It was yet worſe in the days of
<hi>Saul,</hi> between whom and the houſe of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> there was
continual war; and before that in the days of <hi>Samuel</hi> when God
himſelf was their King, we find that they rejected not <hi>Samuel</hi> only,
but God himſelf. And in the times of <hi>Anarchy</hi> when there was no King
in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> there was no peace to him that went out, or to him that
came in, but every man did what ſeemed good in his own eyes. Before this how
long did God bear with the murmuring <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> not in the
wilderneſs only under <hi>Moſes</hi> the meekeſt man upon Earth, and
<hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> the Saint of the Lord, but in <hi>Canaan</hi> againſt God 
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:43568:16"/>himſelf. And from the beginning <hi>Cain</hi> ſlew
<hi>Abel,</hi> and ſo it will be to the end of the world. So that it was a
falſe pretence that the former days were better than <hi>Solomons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It was irreligious, becauſe Religion teacheth us with
all thankfulneſs to acknowledge the bleſſings of God and to ſay with
<hi>Jacob,</hi> I am leſs than the leaſt of all thy mercies, and not to
undervalue them, and expoſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late with God why am I thus? and what is the
cauſe? as if the Almighty had not rewarded us according to our deſerts, or
ought to do nothing but what our reaſon ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves of. They ought to have
conſidered how happy they might have been under ſuch a King, the Son of
ſuch a Father, upon whom God had ſet ſuch Signatures of his own wiſdom,
Clemency and juſtice, whom God made his <hi>Jedidiah</hi> from his birth, and
appeared more than once or twice in many wonderful deliverances of him
againſt the Conſpiracies of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> the diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of
<hi>Joab, Abiathar</hi> and <hi>Shimei</hi> who went to <hi>Gath</hi> to confer
with fugitives and imbroil the kingdom again. If we read of <hi>Solomons</hi>
faults we read of his repentance alſo, this Book of <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> being
a record of his Peniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tials. So that indeed the greateſt cauſe of Evil in
his later days was the libertiniſm of ſome who like ſons of
<hi>Belial</hi> would indure no yoak nor were ſatisfied till they had got an
Indulgence, and were more unſatisfied after they had it. How much better had
it been for them while the true Religion and publick peace were in ſafety, to
have been humble and thankful to God and the King, to reform their own
iniquities and to mourn in ſecret for the Vanities of the Court?</p>
            <p n="3">3. If <hi>Solomons</hi> days had been as bad as the ſins
of theſe men deſerved, yet were it a point of piety to ſubmit to the
mighty hand of God and bear his indignation. This<pb n="24" facs="tcp:43568:17"/>was
<hi>Solomons</hi> preſcript approved by God himſelf, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi>
6.24, <hi>&amp;c. If the people flee before their enemies, if there be famine
or peſtilence.</hi> What is to be done? ſurely not as they did in the
Prophet, <hi>Jer.</hi> 8.20. who did fret themſelves and curſe God and the
King, and look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, as if they would be revenged on all that were above
them, but every man ſhould <hi>ſearch out the plague of his own heart and
repent, and make his ſupplication in Gods houſe ſaying, I have ſinned
and done perverſly, and commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted iniquity,</hi> and then God promiſed to
<hi>hear their prayers, to forgive their ſins and heal their land.</hi> Thus
did King <hi>David</hi> in his diſtreſs, he ſaw the hand of God in it,
<hi>and opened not his mouth becauſe it was the Lords doing;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 9.39.</note> and with this God quieted the men of
<hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Benjamin</hi> in the caſe of <hi>Jeroboam: This thing
is from me.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Kings</hi> 12.24.</note> And though
they did not think ſo of King <hi>Solomon,</hi> yet they ought to think that
God was wiſe enough to diſpoſe of all things for the good of his Church
and people.</p>
            <p>God and his Vicegerents have their <hi>Arcana imperii</hi> not to
be raſhly cenſured or curiouſly inquired into. We ſhould do our duty
and leave the conduct of publick af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs to God whoſe Providence over-rules
all, and it is much better that things ſhould be as God would have them than
as we would, for he acts all towards wiſe and gracious ends, to which though
humane actions like the lower Spheres have a contrary tendency of their own,
yet the firſt mover makes them all tend to his decrees who brings order out
of Confuſion, and all whoſe ways are mercy and truth to them that keep his
Covenant. <hi>Non eſt judicandum de operibus Dei ante quintum actum,</hi> we
are ſhort-ſighted and cannot ſee to the end of Gods works which are begun
in ſecret, &amp; ſometime carried on by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary means, by weak and divers
agents, but he knows how to bring light out of darkneſs and harmonyout of
diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord,<pb n="25" facs="tcp:43568:17"/>and all his providences ſhall end in
Holineſs and beauty too. This is that which <hi>Solomon</hi> obſerved,
<hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ.</hi> 3.11. <hi>God hath made every thing beautiful in its
ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> when it comes to its perfection. Some may think there is no
neceſſity of Thunder and Lightning, Storms and Tempeſts, Froſts and
Cold, yet theſe contribute to the cleanſing of the Air, the health of our
bodies and the fruitfulneſs of the year, as much as calm and Sun-ſhine
days. In checker-work the variety of black and white adds to the beauty; and
ſome works of Providence like the <hi>China</hi> veſſels, are wrought and
perfected in the bowels of the earth and require an age for their Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
but then they come forth ſo tranſparent that every one that conſiders
them may ſay, <hi>This is the Lords doing, and it is marvellous in our
eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. It is irreligious, as being the ready way to deſtroy
Religion, and if that be ruined, we may write <hi>Ichabod</hi> on all things
elſe. And this is not more eaſily deſtroyed than by our murmurings and
contentions about it; this Dove cannot fall but by a dart feathered from her
own wing. The little Foxes within that undermine the Hedge of Diſcipline,
make way for the wild Boar to break in and root up our pleaſant Vines. 'Tis
our crumbling into little factions under pretence of Religion, that expoſeth
us to the enemies of it. If the dangers we fear could but make us unite, our
Union would make us ſafe againſt all the attempts of our common
adverſaries.</p>
            <p n="5">5. It is a tempting and provoking of God in a high degree to
complain of thoſe evils, whoſe cauſes and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies are in our own power.
But while we complain of them with our lips, we draw them down with both our
hands. This is to do as the <hi>Jews</hi> who cryed out <hi>Venient
Romani,</hi> while they were Crucifying the Prince of Peace, and ſo made way
for thoſe <hi>Roman</hi> Armies that brought a perpetual deſolation on
them. If we only<pb n="26" facs="tcp:43568:18"/>make an out-cry againſt Popery, and
inſtead of making up the breaches ſtill inlarge them by quarrelling with
ſuch as are more ready and skilful to do it than our ſelves, that
<hi>Roman</hi> Eagle may make a prey of us all. But if, as God hath founded us
upon a rock, and compaſſed us about with his Salvation as with Walls and
Bulworks, we would be as <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> a people at unity among our
ſelves; if as St. <hi>Paul</hi> adviſeth, we would do our duties to God and
the King without murmurings and diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, thoſe proud Waves that
oppoſe themſelves would be daſht in pieces as hitherto they have been,
and nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the gates of <hi>Rome</hi> nor of Hell prevail againſt us.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, It is irreligious, becauſe it deſtroys the whole
Analogy of Chriſtian Faith, it reflects on Gods Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, as if he wanted
Wiſdom or Goodneſs to Govern the world, and ſets their mouths againſt
Heaven, as that proud <hi>Alfonſus</hi> who ſaid of the Creation, that if
he had been preſent he could have diſpoſed of things in a better method.
It undermines the foundation of all Government in Church and State and
Families, if Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors ſhould be allowed to queſtion the Commands and
Actions of their Superiors; it makes thoſe Chriſtian graces of meekneſs,
patience and obedience, which are injoyned towards evil Governours,
impoſſible. It robs the Soul of that tranquillity and peace which it might
have by reſigning it ſelf to God in well-doing. The ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of grace and
peace will not enter into a diſcontented ſpirit. <hi>God was not in the
earthquake or the whirlwind, but in the ſtill voice,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1
<hi>Kings</hi> 19.11.</note> in the ſedate and chearful Soul. And therefore
<hi>Moſes</hi> calls the murmuring <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
againſt their own Souls, (<hi>i.e.</hi> againſt their peace and comforts of
their life.) 
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 36.38.</note> The Serpent will
devour the Dove, and theſe meager thoughts, like <hi>Pharaohs</hi> lean kine,
eat up better thoughts and affections. To a mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring Soul wiſdom will not
enter. And in a word, it<pb n="27" facs="tcp:43568:18"/>would make the Chriſtian Religion
to ſtink among the heathen: and therefore thou doſt not wiſely to inquire
after ſuch things.</p>
            <p>I have now finiſhed my Diſcourſe on the Text, and if my
hearers will but apply the things ſpoken of <hi>Solomons</hi> Kingdom to our
own, as every ordinary capacity may do, there needs no other Application. I
ſhall end there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as I begun, <hi>Ne dicas,</hi> Say not thou a
confederacy to them that ſay a confederacy to thee, be not allured by their
promiſes, nor affrighted by their threats, for their feet are ſwift to
ſhed bloud, deſtruction and miſery are in their ways, the way of peace
they have not known, and there is no fear of God before their eyes. Learn we of
the men of <hi>Iſachar</hi> in <hi>Davids</hi> days, who <hi>had under
ſtanding of the times, to know what Iſrael ought to do.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 12.32.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Penes vos. eſt rcrum Arbitrium, nobis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licta
eſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequii Gloria,</note> Fear God and Honour the King, and meddle not
with them that are given to change: but leave the Adminiſtration of publick
affairs, and the care of Succeſſion of Crowns and Kingdoms to God and our
Superiors, who are more concerned in them and will provide better for them than
we can do. Let us ſet bounds to our Paſſions by Reaſon, to our Fears
and jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies by Religion, to our Errors by Truth, to our Schiſm by
Charity and an unanimous conſent in the Worſhip of God, and to our
Murmurings by a cheerful improvement of the bleſſings we enjoy: that the
voice of the Turtle may be heard in our Land, even Praiſes to our God for the
wonderful mercies of This day, and for the continuance of them, Prayers for our
King in the words of <hi>Solomons</hi> Subjects, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.66. <hi>The
Lord make the name of</hi> Solomon <hi>better than the name of</hi> David,
<hi>and his Throne greater than the throne of</hi> David; <hi>and they went to
their tents joyful and glad of heart for all the goodneſs that God had done
for</hi> Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>his ſervant, and for Iſrael his people,</hi>
Amen.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
